{"tossups": [{"question": "For over a millennium, this practice was done roughly every 60 years by the Cucuteni-Trypillia culture, possibly to recycle their wattle-and-daub based walls. \u201cPuncturers\u201d made it difficult to combat these events, despite the e\u21b5orts of Sextus Julius Frontinus. Marcus Licinius Crassus infamously took part in these events, then charged a fee to stop them and purchased the a\u21b5ected properties. The Domus Aurea was built over the ruins caused by one of these events in 64 AD. Houses needed to be frequently rebuilt after, for the point, what type of disaster that repeatedly swept through the wooden houses of ancient Rome?", "answer": "<b> fire</b> (accept additional information relating to purposefully setting a<b> fire</b>; accept additional information relating to house<b> fire</b>s)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This event led to a retaliatory bombing of the commercial plane<em> Emperor Kanishka</em>, the first bombing of a 747 and the deadliest aircraft attack prior to 9/11. This event was replicated years later in the less controversial Operation Black Thunder. Operation Woodrose sought to quell protests after this event in the Punjab. This event sought to extricate Jarnail Bhindranwale from a compound in Amritsar. Disgruntled bodyguards assassinated Indira Gandhi in response to, for the point, what June 1984 raid on the holiest site of Sikhism?", "answer": "raid on the<b> Golden Temple</b> of Amritsar (accept Operation<b> Blue Star</b>; prompt on Amritsar before mentioned) Page 2", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this system created by Peter the Great to reform the Russian nobility.", "answer": "Russian<b> annex</b>ation of<b> Crimea</b> (accept descriptions of the Russian Federation<b> taking control of the Crimea</b>n Peninsula; prompt on partial answers, like \u201c(Russian) annexation\u201d) (6) People entering into this system were given the title \u201ccollegiate registrar,\u201d gained the privilege of carrying the Guidon in combat, and were automatically placed in the bottom-most of its fourteen tiers. This system e\u21b5ectively replaced the Mestnichestvo system. Catherine the Great provided an automatic seven-year promotion clause within this system, which created a merit-based bureaucracy of civil service starting in 1722. For the point, name this system created by Peter the Great to reform the Russian nobility. ANSWER:<b> Table of Ranks</b> (or<b> Tabel\u2019o rangakh</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A Saudi and Emirati military intervention against Houthi rebels in this country has led to a humanitarian crisis. The USS<em> Cole</em> bombing took place in, for the point, what country on the Arabian Peninsula where cities like Ta\u2019izz, Aden, and Sana\u2019a have been devastated by civil war?", "answer": "<b> Yemen</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was attacked in one election for a series of communications with a man he had sent on a government trip to Central Asia that resulted in a hunt for the Shaballah; those communications with Nicholas Roerich were known as the \u201cGuru Letters.\u201d This man said \u201cdemocracy was the only true political expression of Christianity\u201d in a speech in which he called for the \u201ccentury of the common man.\u201d This man, Franklin Roosevelt\u2019s first Secretary of Agriculture, finished fourth in the 1948 election while on the Progressive Party ticket. For the point, name this man who served as FDR\u2019s second Vice President.", "answer": "Henry Agard<b> Wallace</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A work by this thinker seeks to prevent the past from becoming \u201cthe gravedigger of the present\u201d by avoiding historicism; that essay, \u201cOn the Use and Abuse of History for Life,\u201d was collected in<em> Untimely</em> <em>Mediations</em>. The title of another work by this man puns on Gotterdammerung and is subtitled \u201cHow to Philosophize with a Hammer.\u201d This man\u2019s fascist sister Elizabeth Forster collected his unpublished writing in<em> The Will to Power</em>. For the point, name this German philosopher who inspired Nazi misreadings of his idea of the \u00a8ubermensch.", "answer": "Friedrich<b> Nietzsche</b> Page 3", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "The ideas that inspired the name of this concept were first presented in a speech alternately called\u201cChance for Peace\u201d or \u201cCross of Iron.\u201d The \u201ciron triangle\u201d combines this group with the influence of Congress and other government representatives. A later speech that popularized this term claimed that an\u201calert and knowledgeable citizenry\u201d must help \u201cguard against the acquisition of unwarranted influence\u201dby it. Dwight Eisenhower\u2019s Farewell Address popularized the name of, for the point, what alliance between a country\u2019s armed forces and its businesses?", "answer": "<b> military-industrial complex</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Hubert Lafayette Sone was given the \u201cOrder of the Blue Jade\u201d for organizing relief in this city. Jesuit Robert de Besange helped create a safety zone in this city following a December 1939 battle. The Fukuo line defended this city, whose Zhonghua gate was breached. Prince Asaka gave a \u201ckill all captives\u201d order in this city, where Toshiaki Mukai and Tsuyoshi Moda had a contest to murder 100 people with swords. John Rabe documented a massacre in this city. Denials of a massacre in this city still plague Japan, which caused, for the point, a \u201crape\u201d in what Chinese city?", "answer": "<b> Nanking</b> (or<b> Nanjing</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. In an interview with Dick Cavett, the central figure of this event claimed that he did it because he didn\u2019t want a certain group to \u201cgrow up only with a negative image of themselves.\u201dThis event would have involved a 15-page speech, but producers demanded it be kept to 60 seconds. Dennis Banks and Russell Means chose Sacheen Littlefeather to take part in this event, which occurred partly in light of \u201crecent happenings at Wounded Knee.\u201d For the point, name this 1973 protest of the treatment of Native Americans in the film industry by an actor who would have received an award for his work on<em> The Godfather</em>.", "answer": "Marlon<b> Brando</b>\u2019s<b> refusal</b> of the<b> Academy Award</b> for Best Actor in 1972 (accept<b> Oscar</b> in place of<b> Academy Award</b>; accept equivalents; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The losing side in this battle su\u21b5ered additional casualties while retreating across the frozen Satschan pond once the ice broke. During this battle, Louis Davout marched 50 miles to reinforce Claude Legrande, whose weak division served to bait an attack on the right flank. This battle, which was secured by Jean Soult\u2019s advance up the Pratzen Heights, led to the Treaty of Pressburg, the end of the War of the Third Coalition, and the dissolution of the Holy Roman Empire. For the point, name this 1805 battle in which a Russian and Austrian alliance was defeated by Napoleon in arguably his greatest victory.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Austerlitz</b> (or the Battle of the<b> Three Emperors</b>) Page 4", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was nominated for President after the convention overruled Caleb Cushing\u2019s decision that a nominee needed two-thirds of the vote. This man noted that the American government was \u201cmade by our fathers on the white basis\u201d in a speech made in Galesburg. This man reaffirmed his stance on popular sovereignty in the face of the Dred Scott decision in his Freeport Doctrine. With Franklin Pierce, this man co-wrote the Kansas-Nebraska Act. For the point, name this Illinois politician who engaged in numerous debates with Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "Stephen A.<b> Douglas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This politician told Harold Wilson that the West would be glad his country was the only one with\u201cinfluence with the Arab governments\u201d before condemning Israel\u2019s unification of Jerusalem during the Six Day War. After this politician rejected Walter Hallstein\u2019s common agricultural policy, he triggered the\u201cEmpty Chair Crisis.\u201d Lester Pearson told this man \u201cCanadians do not need to be liberated\u201d after he proclaimed \u201cVive le Quebec Libre\u201d in Montreal in 1967. For the point, name this first President of the Fifth Republic.", "answer": "Charles<b> de Gaulle</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A deadly incident in this system occurred in 1918 at Malbone Street. William Barclay Parsons was a head engineer in the construction of this system, which Mayor John Hylan proposed expanding with the city-owned IND. This system was constructed by companies such as the IRT and BMT. The Dual Contracts were used to expand this system beyond its initial boundaries, which largely replaced elevated railways. Alfred Beach\u2019s pneumatic railway spurred the development of, for the point, what underground transportation system that includes a station at the Port Authority Bus Terminal in Times Square?", "answer": "<b> New York City Subway</b> (accept descriptive answers that include<b> subway</b> and<b> NYC</b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This composer depicted himself as Robert Storch in the comic opera<em> Intermezzo</em>. He quoted his early opera<em> Guntram</em> as one of the title character\u2019s \u201cworks of peace\u201d in an autobiographical work,<em> A Hero\u2019s</em> <em>Life</em>. This composer, who was commissioned by Joseph Goebbels to write an hymn for the 1936 Olympics, also wrote an opera based on an Oscar Wilde play in which the stepdaughter of King Herod demands the head of John the Baptist and performs the \u201cDance of the Seven Veils.\u201d For the point, name this composer of<em> Salome</em> and tone poems such as<em> Thus Spake Zarathustra</em>.", "answer": "<b> R</b>ichard<b> Strauss</b> (prompt on Strauss) Page 5", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "During this conflict, one side committed the Chuka and Hola massacres and was led by commander-in-chief George Erskine. The Swynnerton Plan attempted to implement land reform during this conflict. Evelyn Baring declared a state of emergency in response to this revolt and helped oversee Operation Anvil, which forcibly relocated people from Nairobi. Dedan Kimathi led Kikuyu rebels during, for the point, what 20th century uprising against British rule in Kenya?", "answer": "<b> Mau Mau</b> rebellion (or uprising, revolt, etc.; accept<b> Kenyan Emergency</b> before \u201cKenya\u201dis said)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "An 1867 article in<em> Harper\u2019s</em> Magazine by George Ward Nichols may have created the legend of this figure, who killed the watch-thieving Davis Tutt in a duel. This man became acquainted with a 12-year old Bu\u21b5alo Bill Cody while serving as a Jayhawker during Bleeding Kansas. This man had his back facing the door when a drunken Jack McCall walked into a saloon and shot him in the back of the head during a game of five-card stud. The \u201cdead man\u2019s hand\u201d was held by, for the point, what Wild West lawman nicknamed \u201cWild Bill?\u201d", "answer": "James Butler \u201cWild Bill\u201d<b> Hickok</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "A noble follower of this ruler named Zopyrus mutilated his own face, setting up a ruse that helped this ruler conquer Babylon. This ruler\u2019s forces were victorious at Lade, allowing for the capture of Miletus and a punitive expedition against Eretria. This ruler may have claimed that Bardiya was an imposter named Gaumata in order to stage a coup against him. The Behistun Inscription was carved on the orders of this ruler, who divided his empire into twenty provinces led by satraps. For the point, name this Persian ruler, the father of Xerxes I.", "answer": "<b> Darius the Great</b> (or<b> Darius I</b>; prompt on Darius)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "One depiction of this building\u2019s interior shows the edge of Cousteau\u2019s sculpture of the<em> Descent from</em> <em>the Cross</em> behind its title figure crowning his wife Josephine. Statues of Old Testament kings taken from this building\u2019s fa\u00b8cade were guillotined in 1793. The middle of three portals on the west side of this building includes a tympanum with reliefs of the Last Judgment. This building is shown faintly with a tricolor flag flying from one of its towers in the background of<em> Liberty Leading the People</em>. For the point, name this cathedral, the seat of the archdiocese of Paris.", "answer": "<b> Notre-Dame</b> de Paris (or<b> Our Lady of Paris</b>) Page 6", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This woman\u2019s support of the foster grandparent program is detailed in the book<em> To Love A Child</em>. This woman\u2019s favorability improved after she dressed as a homeless person at a gridiron dinner. This author of the autobiography<em> My Turn</em> controversially met with the astrologer Joan Quigley on a regular basis. This woman\u2019s response to a girl\u2019s question at an Oakland elementary school, \u201cJust Say No,\u201d named a campaign to stop the spread of drug use. This woman met her future husband while working at MGM in 1949. For the point, name this First Lady, the wife of Ronald Reagan.", "answer": "<b> N</b>ancy<b> Reagan</b> (accept Nancy<b> Davis</b>; accept Anne Frances<b> Robbins</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A ruler from this house tried to pass the Pains and Penalties Bill in order to divorce his wife. William Pitt the Younger argued against making a man from this house regent, claiming that the regent should be chosen by Parliament. A member of this house, the \u201cSailor King,\u201d oversaw the abolishment of slavery and expanded su\u21b5rage with the Great Reform Bill of 1832. The Napoleonic Wars and American Revolution broke out while England was ruled by, for the point, what house whose rulers included William IV, George IV, and George III?", "answer": "House of<b> Hanover</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "During this election year, Champ Clark was an early frontrunner at the convention until Tammany Hall announced its support for him, alienating the progressives. In this election year, the firing of Gi\u21b5ord Pinchot as the head of the Bureau of Forestry caused a split in one political party. A candidate in this election year ran on the ideas of New Freedom, in contrast with another candidate\u2019s New Nationalism. John Schrank attempted to assassinate a candidate in this election year, who then claimed he was as fit as a \u201cbull moose.\u201d For the point, name this election year, in which Woodrow Wilson defeated Theodore Roosevelt and incumbent William Howard Taft.", "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of<b> 1912</b> Page 7", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Carlo Montu advocated using this technology as a support mechanism rather than en masse. A 1921 book claimed that this technology could be used to incite a revolution among the enemy populace, toppling their government. Giulio Douhet advocated the use of this technology, and originated the maxim that a form of this technology \u201calways gets through.\u201d Italy pioneered this technology in a war against Turkey in 1911. For the point, name this war technology whose early uses included completing reconnaissance missions and dropping grenades onto enemy soldiers.", "answer": "<b> air</b> power (or<b> aircraft</b> or<b> airplane</b>s; accept<b> bomber</b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For the point, name these two leaders of Germany and Russia.", "answer": "Adolf<b> Hitler and</b> Joseph<b> Stalin</b> Page 8", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "As revenge against this group, John Norreys attacked Corunna. Martin Padilla led a follow-up to this group\u2019s work that failed at Cape Finisterre. Before this group attacked, Pope Sixtus V claimed the right to collect crusade taxes. Fireships helped defeat this group, which su\u21b5ered a loss at Gravelines [grav-eh-leen] to Sir Francis Drake. The Duke of Medina Sidonia led this group, which failed to join with the Duke of Parma. For the point, name this fleet that attempted an invasion of England in 1588.", "answer": "<b> Spanish Armada</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}